Guide to the Richard Henry Pratt Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Addresses, Diaries, Writings, and Notes, 1862-1953; Series III; (4 boxes)
  - DIARIES
    - War diary, No. 1, with transcript, 2 items, 1862 (Box 19, Folder 683)
    - War diary, No. 2, with transcript, 2 items, 1862 (Box 19, Folder 684)
    - War diary, No. 3, with transcript, 2 items, 1862 (Box 19, Folder 685)
    - War diary, No. 4, with transcript, 2 items, 1862-63 (Box 19, Folder 686)
  - MANUSCRIPTS
    - The Indian No Problem (early draft)
      - Chaps. 1-4, n.d. (Box 20, Folder 687)
      - Chaps. 5-9, n.d. (Box 20, Folder 688)
      - Chaps. 10-17, n.d. (Box 20, Folder 689)
      - Chaps. 18-22, n.d. (Box 20, Folder 690)
      - Chaps. 23-27, n.d. (Box 20, Folder 691)
      - Chaps. 28-31, n.d. (Box 20, Folder 692)
    - The Indian No Problem (later draft)
      - Chaps. 1-4, n.d. (Box 20, Folder 693)
      - Chaps. 5-9, n.d. (Box 20, Folder 694)
      - Chaps. 10-17, n.d. (Box 20, Folder 695)
      - Chaps. 18-22, n.d. (Box 20, Folder 696)
      - Chaps. 23-26, n.d. (Box 20, Folder 697)
      - Chaps. 27-30, n.d. (Box 20, Folder 698)
    - Indian Trails
      - foreword by Mrs. Pratt and Chaps. 3-4 (Box 21, Folder 699)
      - Chaps. 6-9, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 700)
      - Chaps. 10-15, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 701)
      - Chaps. 19, 23-28, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 702)
      - Conclusion (compiled by Mrs. Pratt), n.d. (Box 21, Folder 703)
      - Extra copies from Pratt manuscript (appendix) (Box 21, Folder 704)
      - (4 chapters), n.d. (Box 21, Folder 705)
      - (2 chapters), n.d. (Box 21, Folder 706)
    - Battlefield and Classroom
      See also: Box 22, folders 723-24
      - Manuscript, miscellaneous pages, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 707)
      - Manuscript, miscellaneous pages, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 708)
      - Manuscript, miscellaneous pages, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 709)
      - Manuscript, miscellaneous pages, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 710)
      - Manuscript, miscellaneous pages, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 711)
  - NOTES
    - Notebook: donors to "Charity Fund," 1 item (Box 22, Folder 712)
    - Notebook: list of Indian prisoners, 1 item, 1874 (Box 22, Folder 713)
    - Notebook: list of Indian prisoners, 1 item, 1874 (Box 22, Folder 714)
    - Notes: R. H. Pratt's original memos for Etahdleuh Doanmoe's drawings, 32 items, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 715)
    - R. H. Pratt: miscellaneous writings, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 716)
  - FAMILY WRITINGS
    - Nana Pratt Hawkins: notes and writings (Box 22, Folder 717)
    - Anna L. Pratt: reminiscences, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 718)
    - Mason D. Pratt: notes (Box 22, Folder 719)
    - R. H. Pratt, II?: manuscript on coaching, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 720)
    - R. H. Pratt, II?: notes for manuscript on coaching, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 721)
    - Marion Pratt Stevick: essay on Manimic, 1953 (Box 22, Folder 722)
  - MANUSCRIPTS
    - Battlefield and Classroom
      - Galley proof, chaps. 1-10 (Box 22, Folder 723)
      - Galley proof, chaps. 11-30 (Box 22, Folder 724)
- Photographs and Drawings, 1875-1904; Series IV; (4 boxes)
  Complete and exact identification of individuals, buildings and scenes in the photographs in this series was not possible. The photographs have therefore been grouped together in a general subject arrangement. There are cut film negatives for many of the photographs in this series. These negatives are also arranged by subject and are filed after the photographs. Contact prints have been made for the glass plate negatives, and the originals have been placed in Restricted Fragile, where they may be consulted only with the approval of the appropriate curator. This series also contains several sketchbooks of drawings made by Indian prisoners at St. Augustine, Florida, and Indian students at Carlisle, Pennsylvania.
  - PHOTOGRAPHS
    - Carlisle Indian Industrial School, 9 items: (Box 23, Folder 725)
    - Carlisle School, 3 items, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 726)
    - Carlisle School graduating classes, 6 items, 1889-92 (Box 23, Folder 727)
    - Carlisle School graduating classes, 6 items, 1894-1900, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 728)
    - Carlisle School students, 8 items, 1878-81 (Box 23, Folder 729)
    - Carlisle School students, 13 items, 1894-1903, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 730)
    - Carlisle School students, 10 items, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 731)
    - Carlisle School teachers and benefactors, 8 items, 1895-1904, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 732)
    - Fort Apache and White Mountain Indians, 3 items (Box 23, Folder 733)
    - Indian chiefs, 3 items (Box 23, Folder 734)
    - Indian drawings, 11 items (Box 23, Folder 735)
    - Indian miscellaneous, 5 items (Box 23, Folder 736)
    - Indian women, 11 items (Box 23, Folder 737)
    - New Mexican Indians, 8 items (Box 23, Folder 738)
    - R. H. Pratt, 8 items, 1886-1900, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 739)
    - Contact print of R. H. Pratt color slide, 1 item, 1914 (Box 23, Folder 739a)
    - R. H. Pratt, W. A. Cleveland, and F. A. Wright (Sioux Commission), 1 item, 1889 (Box 23, Folder 740)
    - R. H. Pratt and General Cooke, 1 item (Box 23, Folder 741)
    - R. H. Pratt, miscellaneous, 6 items, 1890, n.d. (Box 23a, Folder 742)
    - St. Augustine, Florida: Fort Marion, 5 items, n.d. (Box 23a, Folder 743)
      - Fort Marion (stereograms), 18 items, n.d. (Box 23a, Folder 744)
      - Indian prisoners, 3 items, 1875 (Box 23a, Folder 745)
      - Indian prisoners, 15 items, 1875-78 (Box 23a, Folder 746)
      - Indian prisoners (stereograms), 2 items (Box 23a, Folder 747)
      - Stereograms, miscellaneous, 7 items, n.d. (Box 23a, Folder 748)
    - Standing Bear, Luther, with biographical note, 1 item (Box 23a, Folder 749)
    - Stereograms, miscellaneous, 6 items, n.d. (Box 23a, Folder 750)
    - Miscellaneous and unidentified, 3 items (Box 23a, Folder 751)
    - Lantern slides of selected visual materials in the Pratt Papers, assorted subjects, 38 items, n.d. (Box 23b, Folder 751a)
  - NEGATIVES
    - Carlisle Indian Industrial School, 3 items (Box 24, Folder 752)
    - Carlisle Indian Industrial School, students, 22 items (Box 24, Folder 753)
    - Indian drawings, 25 items (Box 24, Folder 754)
    - R. H. Pratt, 6 items, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 755)
    - St. Augustine, Florida: Fort Marion and Indian prisoners, 5 items (Box 24, Folder 756)
    - Miscellaneous, 6 items, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 757)
    - Contact prints for glass negatives: R. H. Pratt, 2 items, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 758)
    - Empty folder (Box 24, Folder 759)
      This folder was previously identified as glass negative: R. H. Pratt, 1 item / n.d. This item, a color slide portrait of Pratt, has been moved to box 23, folder 739a
    - Contact prints for glass negative: R. H. Pratt, 1 item, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 760)
    - Contact prints for glass negatives: R. H. Pratt, 2 items, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 761)
    - Contact print for glass negative: R. H. Pratt, 1 item, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 762)
    - Contact prints for glass negatives: R. H. Pratt on his horse, Kiowa, 2 items, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 763)
    - Empty folder (Box 24, Folder 764)
      This folder was previously identified as glass slides: assorted subjects (duplicates of photos), 38 items / n.d. These lantern slides have been moved to box 23b, folder 751a
  - DRAWINGS
    - Buffalo Meat's price list (drawing), 1 item, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 765)
    - Drawings by Indian prisoners at St. Augustine, Florida (sketchbook), 1 item, 1876 (Box 24, Folder 766)
    - Drawings by Indian prisoners at St. Augustine, Florida (sketchbook), 1 item, 1875-78 (Box 24, Folder 767)
    - Drawings by Indian (Ohetoint?) at Carlisle, Pennsylvania (sketchbook), 1 item, 1880 (Box 24, Folder 768)
    - Drawings by Etahdleuh Doanmoe (Box 24, Folder 769)
    - Display on Etahdleuh Doanmoe
- Clippings and Miscellaneous Publications, 1874-1953; Series V; (5 boxes)
  This series contains several folders of newspaper clippings about R. H. Pratt, the Carlisle Indian Industrial School, and other Indian topics. Also included are fourteen scrapbooks of clippings and memorabilia relating to various Indian subjects. Miscellaneous magazines, pamphlets, and Carlisle School publications are also filed in this series. The series is arranged alphabetically by type of material. The newspaper clippings are arranged chronologically and the scrapbooks are grouped together under the name of the compiler when it is known.
  - NEWSPAPERS, MAGAZINES, ETC.
    - Carlisle School publications: annual reports, 3 items, 1890, 1899 (Box 25, Folder 770)
    - The Arrow, 3 items, 1904, 1907 (Box 25, Folder 771)
    - The Carlisle Arrow and Red Man, 5 items, 1917 (Box 25, Folder 772)
    - The Carlisle Arrow and Red Man, 3 items, 1918 (Box 25, Folder 773)
    - Catalogue of the Indian Industrial School, 1 item, 1902 (Box 25, Folder 774)
    - The Indian Helper, 3 items, 1897 (Box 25, Folder 775)
    - Invitations, menus, programs, miscellaneous, 13 items, n.d. (Box 25, Folder 776)
    - The Morning Star, 1 item, 1883 (Box 25, Folder 777)
    - Names of Graduates, 2 items, 1914 (Box 25, Folder 778)
    - The Red Man, 1 item, 1896 (Box 25, Folder 779)
    - The Red Man and Helper, 5 items, 1904 (Box 25, Folder 780)
    - Magazines
      - "The Alaskan Fisherman," 1 item, 1924 (Box 25, Folder 781)
      - "The Army and Navy Journal," 1 item, 1894
      - "The Indian School Journal," 1 item, 1924 (Box 25, Folder 782)
      - "The Mentor," 1 item, 1924 (Box 25, Folder 783)
      - "The Native American," 1 item, 1924 (Box 25, Folder 784)
      - "Our Young People," 3 items, 1897 (Box 25, Folder 785)
      - "The Regional Review," 1 item, 1940 (Box 25, Folder 786)
      - Miscellaneous clippings, n.d. (Box 25, Folder 787)
    - Newspapers
      - "The Chautauqua Assembly," 1 item, 1904 (Box 25, Folder 788)
      - Clippings, 1877-99 (Box 25, Folder 789)
      - Clippings, 1900-04 (Box 25, Folder 790)
      - Clippings re: Pratt's speech attacking Indian Bureau, 1904 May (Box 25, Folder 791)
      - Clippings, 1907-09 (Box 25, Folder 792)
      - Clippings, 1911-17 (Box 25, Folder 793)
      - Clippings, 1919-23 (Box 25, Folder 794)
      - Clippings re: Pratt's death, 1924 (Box 25, Folder 795)
      - Clippings, 1925-55, n.d. (Box 25, Folder 796)
  - PAMPHLETS AND SCRAPBOOKS
    - Pamphlets: addresses by E. B. Merit, n.d. (Box 26, Folder 797)
    - Pamphlets: miscellaneous government publications, n.d. (Box 26, Folder 798)
    - Scrapbook of clippings, 1 item, 1878-80 (Box 26, Folder 799)
    - Scrapbook of clippings, 1 item, 1880-1916 (Box 27, Folder 800)
    - Scrapbook of clippings, 1 item, 1887 (Box 27, Folder 801)
    - Scrapbook of clippings, 1 item, 1890-91 (Box 27, Folder 802)
    - Scrapbook of clippings, 1 item, 1894, 1897 (Box 27, Folder 803)
    - Scrapbook of clippings belonging to R. H. Pratt, 1 item, 1881-82 (Box 28, Folder 804)
    - Scrapbook of clippings compiled by A. Laura Pratt, 1 item, 1874-78 (Box 28, Folder 805)
    - Scrapbook of clippings compiled by A. Laura Pratt, 1 item, 1879-81 (Box 28, Folder 806)
    - Scrapbook of clippings compiled by A. Laura Pratt, 1 item, 1885-86 (Box 28, Folder 807)
    - Scrapbook of clippings compiled by A. Laura Pratt, 1 item, 1898-1929 (Box 29, Folder 808)
    - Scrapbook of clippings compiled by Jeanette Senseney?, 1 item, 1899-1904 (Box 29, Folder 809)
    - Scrapbook of clippings compiled by Marion Pratt (15 articles from the Christian Science Monitor ), 1 item, n.d. (Box 29, Folder 810)
    - Scrapbook of clippings re: Sioux Commission of 1888, 1 item, n.d. (Box 29, Folder 811)
    - Scrapbook of clippings re: Sioux Commission of 1888, 1 item, n.d. (Box 29, Folder 812)
- Special Files, 1878-1963; Series VI; 0.25; (1 box)
  Special Files contains miscellaneous and unidentified materials pertaining to Pratt, the Carlisle Indian Industrial School, the Indian prisoners at St. Augustine, Florida, the Sioux Commission of 1888, and other topics. The materials are grouped together by subject and alphabetically under each subject heading.
  - Carlisle Indian Industrial School: article on Commandant's Quarters, 1953 (Box 30, Folder 813)
  - History of the Outing (author unknown), n.d. (Box 30, Folder 814)
  - "Outing" forms and rules (Box 30, Folder 815)
  - Unidentified articles on the school, 1901, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 816)
  - Report on returned students, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 817)
  - Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 818)
  - Correspondence re: "Good Housekeeping" article by V. L. Connolly (mimeographed copies), 1929 (Box 30, Folder 819)
  - Indian prisoners and Hampton Institute -- miscellaneous articles, 1878 (Box 30, Folder 820)
  - R. H. Pratt: bills, statements, etc., n.d. (Box 30, Folder 821)
  - Biographical materials, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 822)
  - Biographical materials, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 823)
  - Biographical materials on related families, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 824)
  - Certificates, deeds, passports, etc., n.d. (Box 30, Folder 825)
  - Memorial plaque at Carlisle Barracks, 1955 (Box 30, Folder 826)
  - C. S. Rhodes' report on Indian administration, 1933 (Box 30, Folder 827)
  - St. Augustine, Florida -- miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 828)
  - The Sioux Commission of 1888 -- miscellaneous materials (Box 30, Folder 829)
  - General H. L. Scott's speech on the government and the Indian, 1929 (Box 30, Folder 830)
  - Robert M. Utley's introduction to R. H. Pratt's book, 1963 (Box 30, Folder 831)
  - Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 832)
  - Miscellaneous illustrations, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 833)
- Stand Alone Art Boxes, (2 boxes)
  - DRAWINGS BY ETAHDLEUH DOANMOE
    The drawings by Etahdleuh Doanmoe are on ledger book paper. Some include manuscript caption titles; others have brief descriptions typed on them. Some sheets are numbered and have been arranged sequentially. Other, unnumbered drawings have been interfiled as appropriately as possible. They are identified on the list below by placing their numbers in brackets.
    - (1) Kiowa camp on reservation. Council (Box 31)
    - (2) Fort Sill (Box 31)
    - (3) Confrontation of Indians and U.S. Army (Box 31)
    - (4) Capt. Pratt and Kicking Bird meeting Kiowas (Box 31)
    - (5) Night of the surrender -- dance -- Indian lodges (Box 31)
    - (6) Passing of prisoners in front of Medicine Bluffs (Box 31)
    - (7) Prisoners entering Fort Sill (Box 31)
    - (8) 70 warriors placed in irons (Box 31)
    - (9) Loading prisoners in army wagons (Box 31)
    - (10) Camp en route to railroad (Box 31)
    - [11] Prisoners arriving at Caddo, 1875 May 5 (Box 31)
    - [12] Roll-call, Fort Marion, [18]75-78 (Box 31)
    - [13] Camp on Anastasia Island, 1876 (Box 31)
    - [14] Indians moving cannon. Ft. Marion, 1876 (Box 31)
    - (15) Arrival in Nashville, Tennessee, attempted suicide (Box 31)
    - (16) Suicide left in Nashville (Box 31)
    - (17) Arrival in Jacksonville, Florida (Box 31)
    - (18) Transferral from train to steamboat at Jacksonville (Box 31)
    - [19] Arrival in St. Augustine (Box 31)
    - (20) Inside Fort Marion. Indians on terreplein (Box 31)
    - (21) Catching sharks at St. Augustine harbor (Box 32)
    - (22) Young Kiowas dressed for a ceremonial visit (Box 32)
    - (23) Prisoners' camp, Anastasia Island (Box 32)
    - (24) Kiowa banquet back home (Box 32)
    - (25) Omaha dance at St. Augustine (Box 32)
    - (26) Kiowas killing buffalo (Box 32)
    - (27) Trip to Matanzas (Box 32)
    - (28) Weekly religious service at Fort (Box 32)
    - (29) Classes for prisoners at Fort (Box 32)
    - (30) Capt. Pratt's residence at Fort (Box 32)
    - (31) Prisoners' military drill (Box 32)
    - [32] Prisoners moving the Chapel St. Augustine, 1877 (Box 32)
    - [33] Indian council (Box 32)
    - [34] [Three ships] (Box 32)
    - [35] [Railroads and houses] (Box 32)
    - [36] Plaza and Cathedral, St. Augustine (Box 32)
    - [37] U.S. Cavalry (Box 32)
- Oversize, (1 box)
  - PHOTOGRAPHS AND DRAWINGS
    - Buffalo Meat's price list (drawing), 1 item, n.d. (Box 33, Folder 834)
    - Original title page and first sketch of Drawings by Indian prisoners at St. Augustine, Florida (sketchbook), 1876 (Box 33, Folder 834a)
    - Original page 16 of Drawings by Indian prisoners at St. Augustine, Florida (sketchbook), 1876 (Box 33, Folder 834b)
    - Drawing of Kiowa on horse laid in loose to Drawings by Indian prisoners at St. Augustine, Florida (sketchbook), 1876 (Box 33, Folder 834c)
    - Display on Etahdleuh Doanmoe, n.d. (Box 33, Folder 835)
- Restricted Fragile, (3 boxes)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 23, folder 739a (Box 34, Folder 836)
  - Box 24, folder 758 (Box 34, Folder 837)
  - Box 24, folder 760 (Box 34, Folder 838)
  - Box 24, folder 761 (Box 34, Folder 839)
  - Box 24, folder 762 (Box 34, Folder 840)
  - Box 24, folder 763 (Box 34, Folder 841)
  - Glass plate negatives of prints in box 37 (Box 42)
  - Slide viewer, circa 1918 (Box 43)
- December 1976 Acquisition, 1871-1972; Series VII; 1.33; (4 boxes) + 3 broadsides
  The December 1976 Acquisition contains printed material, ephemera, and photographs pertaining to Pratt and the Carlisle School; material concerning Pratt's service in the United States Army; genealogical materials pertaining to Pratt; correspondence; photographs and negatives of Native American camps, the Pratt family, and trips to Alaska and New Mexico; sea beans polished by Native American prisoners at Fort Marion, Florida; and maps showing Indian reservations within the United States.
  - Printed material pertaining to Pratt, the Carlisle School, and Native Americans, 1881-1972; 13 (Box 35)
  - Printed material pertaining to Pratt, the Carlisle School, and Native Americans, 1881-1972; 8 (Box 36)
  - Carlisle School ephemera, 1894-1917
  - Photographs taken at Carlisle School, undated
  - University of Cincinnati vs. Carlisle Indians football memento program, 1897-1897
  - Biographical sketch of Pratt, undated
  - Army records, 1903-1905, undated
  - US Army War College folder concerning Mrs. S. Clark Seelye's visit, 1969-1969
  - Chronology of Pratt's tenure at the Carlisle School, undated
  - Genealogical materials on Pratt compiled by Mrs. S. Clark Seelye, undated
  - Letters from M. B. Anderson to Pratt, 1878-1881
  - Richard Henry Pratt birthday book: Greetings on the Year of His 80th Birthday, manuscript notes from friends and family with photographs and ephemera laid in, and compiled by his daughter, Nana Pratt Hawkins, 3 (Box 37)
  - Prints from glass negatives in Box 42, undated
  - Alaskan trip photographs, 1896-1896
  - New Mexico photographs, 1896-1896
  - Pratt family photographs, circa 1900, undated
  - Sea beans polished by Native American prisoners at Fort Marion, St. Augustine, Florida, 1875-1878
  - Newspaper clippings of engravings of Native Americans, undated (Box 38 (Oversize))
  - The Carlisle Indian School march sheet music, 1896-1896
  - Photographs of Kiowa and Comanche camps, undated
  - Copy of a fragment of Pratt's manuscript on the history of the Carlisle School, with copies of correspondence concerning the distribution of the manuscript, 1929-1934, undated
  - Photograph of Native American prisoners shortly after their arrival at Fort Marion, 1871-1871
  - Map Showing Indian Reservations Within the Limits of the United States, Compiled Under the Direction of the Honorable W. A. Jones, Commissioner of Indian Affairs, 1898-1898 (Box 39 (Broadside))
  - Map Showing Indian Reservations Within the Limits of the United States, 1912-1912
  - Photograph of Dakota Indian boys from Rosebud and Pine Ridge Sioux agencies, Dakota: the first party to arrive at the Indian Industrial School, Carlisle, Pennsylvania, 1879 October 6 (Box 40 (Broadside))
  - Photograph of Dakota Indian girls from Rosebud and Pine Ridge Sioux agencies, Dakota: the first party to arrive at the Indian Industrial School, Carlisle, Pennsylvania, 1879 October 6 (Box 41 (Broadside))
  - Slide viewer, circa 1918 (Box 43)